hello and welcome it's September 13th
2024 and we're in active inference model
stream
14.1 with ranway talking about value of
information and reward specification in
active inference there will be a
presentation then we'll have a
discussion and looking forward to
people's comments and questions thank
you again for joining and looking
forward to the
presentation yeah sure so I'll just dive
into it um yeah so thanks again for uh
the invitation and uh uh so this paper
is about the value of information and
then some aspects about reward
specification in active inference but it
also touches on PD
pce and so the motivation is very simple
so
was simply trying to understand the
expected free energy objective for
Action planning in active
infant um and the nice thing about the
EF objective uh which makes it appealing
objective for uh a variety of uh people
in a variety of domains is that it has a
very intuitive decomposition as the sum
of the expected value term and epistemic
value term and then so the expected
value term is this term that encourages
the agent to obtain reward or uh achieve
their preferred state of the world um
because it's simply the cross entropy
between the predicted uh future
observations given some actions and the
preferred observations P
TOA um the second term epistemic value
is what makes active inference uh or
make what makes EF very interesting so
the epistemic value ter
is defined as the expected K Divergence
between uh future uh posterior so belief
about future States given future
observations and the predicted um
distribution of future States um so what
this term does is it quantifies how far
is the future posterior from the future
prior which essentially quantifies the
amount of belief update so if you op
this term then it essentially encourages
the agent to take actions that would
lead to a higher amount of belief update
so higher amount of information obtained
about the
environment um so experimentally people
have found that uh optimizing this
objective led to some very interesting
Behavior so on the left hand side here
we have an example from one of Alex
papers uh where he compared the uh what
we call the state coverage of reward
maximizing agents versus active
influence agents uh in this uh simple
environment called a mountain car where
the state of the agent is uh represented
by its position and velocity so we see
that active inference agent has a much
larger coverage of the state space so it
spreads more territory of the state
Space versus the reward maximizing
agents and so this um potentially allows
the agent to do is to learn a better and
more comprehensive model of the
environment which it also turns out that
having such a model enables better
action selection and actually achieving
higher
reward um so on the right hand side we
have an example from one of my papers so
I I did a lot of study on modeling human
driving behavior and this is one of the
examples where we have a car called the
ego vehicle driving down the road
and then on the side of the road we have
a large truck which potentially obscure
the view of a pedestrian but we don't
actually know whether The Pedestrian
exists or not exists but if The
Pedestrian does exist we assume or
rather the ego vehicle believes that
it's going to cross the road so we don't
want to cause any conflict with the
pachan who's trying to cross the road so
this egole vehicle does as the
consequence of optimizing EF is that it
will nudge slightly to the left of the
road to gain view of The Pedestrian and
if it sees that The Pedestrian doesn't
exist then it will return to the center
of the road and carry on with the
optimal uh Speed without ever having to
stop for The Pedestrian um so these
behaviors are very interesting and it
highlights uh the value of encouraging
the agent to explore and gain
information about the environment and
this is usually understood as the main
differentiator um between active
inference and some of the other frame
works for decision making such as
reinforcement
learning but one somewhat contradictory
fact um is that um actually Bas basian
and met reinforcement learning are
already known to optimally trade off
explo exploitation so here we have an
example from one of the more recent meta
surveys where um uh so this is actually
a very common Benchmark in met r where
we would start an agent in the center of
the circle and then the goal position
which is unknown to the agent will be
somewhere along the circle but again
it's never known to the agent so what
the agent has to do is to explore along
the circle to find the goal so basically
what it does is it'll pick a position
along the circle and it'll just Trace
along the circle until it arrives at the
uh goal position so this is the uh the
optimal strategy for this setting and
and we see that it's already being
demonstrated by metao so this begs the
question even more of what is the
relationship between active inference
and Basin
ail um and the main idea of the paper or
rather the main Insight that we're
trying to offer is that EF can be
understood as an approximation to the
base optimal RL policy and specifically
via the information reward shaping uh of
the F
objective um so to unpack this I will U
do a very brief review of uh some
preliminary preliminary annotations on
mdps and active inference and then we
will introduce a few analysis tools from
mdp Theory which will allow us to better
understand and appreciate uh the notion
of value of information which then will
allow us to derive the main results of
the paper and just close up with some
discussion and more and and some other
interactive uh
activities um yeah so so the
preliminaries will be very brief because
most people uh in The Institute I
believe are the experts in these topics
um so this is the uh regular formalism
for mdps and then um the objective of an
agent in mdp is usually to maximize
discounted cumulative rewards so I have
Chen chosen to use the infinite Horizon
uh setting with discounting because it
makes the analysis a bit easier um but
one so the so the only thing I wanted to
highlight on this page is that uh the
classic mdp Theory says that for a given
mdp with known transition probabilities
and known reward function there always
exists at least one deterministic
stationary Marian policy and then the
value function of the policy which is
the value accured by the policy in mdp
can be computed from the bman
equations um and then so another
ingredient that we need is going is
partially absorbable mdp which is just
an extension of
mdps where uh the state variable now is
no longer directly observable to the
agent but the agent can observe another
signal o that's usually correlated with
the states um but because the agent can
no longer observe the state then if you
condition your policy only on the most
recent observation you don't really have
um sufficient information for uh taking
optimal actions so in general for p DPS
the uh optimal policy has to be
conditioned on the entire history which
uh as it accumulates can tend to an
infinite length um so here we need to uh
recall another very uh
important result from P DP Theory which
is that the belief state which can be
computed from the Bas in belief update
is a sufficient statistic of the entire
history which means that if you
condition your policy on a belief State
then you don't have the condition of
policy on the entire history and then
once you do that you can Define the
value function also in terms of the
belief so we have What's called the
belief action value function the belief
value function
um so this belief State view of pal DPS
is very interesting because it says that
for any given pal DP you have an
equivalent uh mdp that's defined on the
space of belief uh beliefs uh equivalent
in the sense that it would yield the
same optimal policy for the belief mdp
and the
pmdp and then uh this belief mdp would
have its corresponding belief action
reward and belief transition Dynamics so
the belief action reward is defined
simply as the weighted average of the
state action reward by the beliefs and
what's interesting about this belief mdp
is how the belief transition Dynamics is
defined um so you can understand this by
looking at this uh these two terms on
the right hand side so this basically
says that in order to transition um the
belief from one time step to the ne next
time step to get B Prime the first thing
you're going to do is to draw uh a
future observation um or sometimes I
call it counterfactual future
observation o Prime from the posterior
predictive of the observation
distribution under the current belief
and you're going to you you then you're
going to perform a basing update on this
counterfactual observation to get the
next belief and so because the marginal
distribution over the observation is in
general stochastic this makes the belief
transition Dynamics also stochastic um
so this is the belief mdp the equivalent
belief mdp for the PDP and then we I
will refer to this as the base optimal
belief mdp because the policy computed
from such a belief mdp would be would be
the base optimal policy for the pal
DP um so then we have active infant
which similar to the canonical pum DP
framework has an infant step and a
planning step and then so the difference
between active inference and PD the
regular P DP is instead of
Performing um exact basing update will
perform variational
updates but um because from the
variation inference literature we know
that if the variational distribution qfs
is chosen appropriately then it would
have to be equal to the exact Basin
update so this doesn't really introduce
too much difference from the classic um
P DP framework the main difference
between active inference uh and the
class of P DP is that the agent would um
instead of optimizing reward the agent
op minimizes expected free energy uh and
uh I I wrote the uh this form of EF here
which I believe is more General um
sometimes it's sometimes referred to as
the energy entropy uh
decomposition um so something I want to
remark on this page is that whenever we
talk about EF we need to be very precise
about the definition of different cues
because there are too many cues in
active inference and in EF um and here I
Define the Q over future States as the
product of U Future marginal State
distributions uh this is not because I
invented it it I'm just uh writing this
um uh writing with the usual the the
usual definition of uh efp in a more
formal way and explicitly call out that
this is the product of future marginal
States um and then so one more step to
get the pragmatic and epic value
decomposition of e is that we would have
to define the energy function or the
preference distribution to have
preference only on the observations and
then we can split up the energy entropy
decomposition into the pragmatic and
epistemic value
decomposition um so what this
characterization allows us to do is that
we can now see EF as a specific type of
belief mdp where um it it would be
different from the base optimal belief
mdp but it would still have its own
belief action reward and belief
transition Dynamics so if we look at the
belief action reward it's simply the sum
of the one-step pragmatic value which I
denote with r TAA and the one-step
epistemic value and if we unpack the
one-step pragmatic value we can actually
write it as a linear combination of a
state action reward and this is because
of the linearity of the expectation uh
which is used to define uh the pragmatic
value um but the linearity doesn't hold
for the epistemic value and in fact the
epistemic values concave in the
beliefs um another interesting aspect
about the belief transition Dynamics for
EF is that it doesn't so different from
the base optimal belief transition
Dynamics it doesn't contain the
counterfactual observation o Prime so
what it means is that uh instead of
drawing a counterfactual observation
from the current uh posterior predictive
marginal and doing a counterfactual
update you would just directly propagate
your current belief to the next uh State
marginal and so this uh is sometimes
called the open loop belief updating in
the literature in a way that's analogous
to open loop control so that you would
update your belief without taking into
account of the next observation but only
during planning not during execution
which we'll come back to later um but
the belief mdp view of EF uh would tell
us that uh there exists an optimal
deterministic markovian policy simply
due to the characterization as an
mdp um so this with all of these um
precise characterizations we can also
make our main question uh more precise
um and so we saw that EF uses the open
loop belief Dynamics with an added
information
reward where whereas the base optimal uh
belief mdp uses the regular uh can the
regular linear combination of State
action words and a close loop belief
Dynamics so can can we understand uh
these modifications in efv as an
approximation to the base optimal belief
mdp and in turn the base optimal policy
so that's the question we're trying to
pursue uh in this
paper um and then so in order to answer
that we need to introduce some tools
from mdp Theory um so the first set of
Concepts we introduce are the policy
advantage and the model advantage and
for the sake of discussion now we just
understand them as some abstract notion
of error measures of uh the policy and
the model and the reason why I say that
is that if you look at the definition of
the policy Advantage for example so it's
defined as difference between two value
functions so for the first value
function the action is uh taken from the
argument of uh the advantage function
whereas in the second value function the
acttion is taken from uh this policy Pi
which is used Define the value function
so the reason why I say this can be
understood as an error measure is that
if the action a is more or less the same
as the action drawn from the policy Pi
then the advantage function will be zero
so there will be no difference between
between them so this essentially
characterize how much is action a
different from an action that would have
been chosen by uh the policy that's used
to define the value function and then
basically more or less the same idea
holds for model Advantage but instead of
measuring the difference in the actions
we're measuring the difference in the
two Dynamics by saying that if I draw a
next state S Prime from Dynamics P Prime
and another next state s double Prime
from Dynamics P how is the value of S
Prime different from s double Prime so
if P Prime is actually equal to P then
there is no model Advantage so this
thing measures the difference between
the two
models um two other Concepts we need to
know uh one is effective Horizon so this
is basically
introduced uh uh as an analog of
planning Horizon for infinite Horizon
discounted problem so it's defined as
one over one minus the discount uh
discount Factor gamma so it's basically
saying how many time steps do I need to
accumulate until the geometric
discounting that's usually used in uh in
RL setting uh is zero and then the
normalized occupancy measure is
essentially the uh stationary or
marginal State action distribution along
the mark of chain of rolling out a
policy in a
Dynamics so this kind of essentially
characterizes the equilibrium behavior
of the system
um and then so with these Concepts we
have our first analysis tool uh which I
call performance difference in
mismatched andd pce so what we trying to
do in this LMA is the following so we we
say that we're gonna look at two
policies pi and Pi Prime and then both
policies are optimal with with with
respect to their own mdps which we
denote as M and M Prime and we we're
going to say that these two mdps would
share the same state and action space
same initial State distribution and the
same discount Factor but they could
potentially have different rewards and
different
Dynamics so this is this this is very
similar to the comparison of the EF
policy and the base optimal policy where
um they share the same spaces but they
have different rewards and different
Dynamics so this is basically our tool
to to quantify their difference and then
so what this Lima said move on to say is
that um we're going to look at the
performance difference between these two
policies but both of them will be
evaluated in environment M and because
uh policy Pi is by definition the
optimal policy for uh mdp or environment
M then there's no way that Pi Prime is
going to do better than Pi uh so that's
why this quantity is also called a
regret uh so we're going to interchange
with calling it regret or performance
difference but um basically this
relationship here shows that the regret
can be decomposed into three terms so
the first term is the advantage of the
actions drawn from uh uh policy Pi which
I would uh I call it expert distribution
because it's the better policy in this
setting and then the second and third
term um are defined in terms of the
model advantage and iuse um notation or
abuse labeling to call it also the
reward
advantage and then so you can understand
this
relationship uh by um saying that if R
and RP Prime are equal and then p and p
Prime are equal then there's no reward
model advantage or disadvantage between
the two policies and because of that
then there's also no policy Advantage
then the regret would be
zero um so and and so the nice thing
about this relationship is that if we
put an absolute value sign uh over it
and then we have um do some algebra then
we can actually obtain an upper bound on
the regret uh that's defined in terms of
the policy Advantage reward advantage Ag
and uh the difference between the two
Dynamics so from now on I will actually
call reward and policy Advantage um
reward and pause the error because
that's to some extent what they
represent so what we see here on the
right hand side is that the coefficients
for these different terms are different
so the coefficients for the reward and
policy era are linear in the planning
Horizon 1 over 1 minus gamma whereas the
coefficient for the
uh Dynamics difference is quadratic or
squared in a planning Horizon so it says
that if we're uh making errors or
mistakes along all of these dimensions
then the rate at which the Dynamics
model error accumulate is going to be
much faster than the rate at which
policy and reward error
accumulates um another thing to remark
about this relationship is that it can
be a little bit conservative
because um sometimes even if you make
mistakes with your choice of Dynamics
you can actually make it up by
uh choosing the reward function to be
different from the optimal reward so
basically whatever if if you incur some
disadvantage in the Dynamics then you
can choose to gain some advantage in the
reward so that it canel out and then so
basically I'm going to show that this is
what happens with um the EF Poli EF
policy compared to the base optimal
policy um yeah so let's with this let's
refine our main question a little bit
more so we're trying to understand EF as
an approximation to the base optimal uh
believe mdp and it's specifically the
way in which um it approximates that is
via this reward shaping term to cancel
out the this disadvantage uh due to
using open loop belief
Dynamics uh so before we do that we um
we should review the notion of value of
information uh which will give us clue
um and also make better connections
between uh these two
topics so the value of information uh
the most popular definition was given by
Ronald Howard
1966 where he defines it as the reward
that a decision maker is willing to give
away if they could have their
uncertainty resolved um by some magician
for example and if you commit to this
definition then you can quantify the
value of information simply as the
difference between the expected value
given perfect information and expected
value without perfect information and
then one very appealing fact about this
is that because an optimal decision
maker cannot do worse by having more
information then the expected value
perfect information is always not
negative at least in the single agent
setting um but the thing about pmdp is
that in general you cannot just provide
agent with perfect information um
usually what happens is um the
environment provides the agent with an
observation that provides indirect
information about the environment um so
we need to essentially make an extension
of the expected value of perfect
information for the P DP setting and uh
and it's basically very straightforward
and I would just label it as the
expected value of perfect observation
because we can make an observation
rather than be given perfect information
and this is sometimes uh called the the
value of imperfect information uh from
the decision Theory literature and the
definition again is just the difference
between the expected value given the
perfect observation versus without the
perfect observation and uh the non-
negativity uh result apply again in the
setting and then so to apply the
expected value of perfect observation to
the pal DP setting we then have to take
into account the the sequential nature
of decision making and once we add that
it actually turns out that uh the
definition of EV in the setting is um
the expected value using the canonical
linear combination rewards plus the open
loop belief updating whereas the
expected value given perfect observation
uh is the same as the base optimal value
function so so this is very interesting
and um it also so because uh the
definition of the expected value uses
open loop Dynamics it sort of serve as a
bridge between the base optimal policy
um the active inference well actually
maybe I put it here the active inference
um policy whereas the open loop policy
is in the middle um because this open
loop value function takes one turn from
the base optimal policy and takes
another term the belief transition
Dynamics term from the active inference
policy um so again the non- negativity
of uh the value of perfect observation
appli in a setting because uh you
increase the planning Horizon you're
basically acre the non- negativity of
value of information along your planning
Horizon um so this is great but uh the
problem with this proposition is that it
doesn't really tell us how much uh is
the closed loop or base optimal policy
better than open loop policy uh and it
also doesn't take into account of the
fact that usually uh in applications
even even though we would plan a policy
in open loop when we deploy the policy
we usually still deploy the policy in
close loop by allowing an agent to
observe the environment and update their
belief and if we consider all of this
then uh we we would actually need to
compare um the Clos Loop policy and open
loop policy using the performance
difference in mismatch mdp where both
policies are tested on the ground Truth
uh pum DP which we allow the agent to
update their
beliefs um so if we do that if we make
comparison that way then one thing we
know is that the main contributor to the
performance difference between the two
policies is due to uh model advantage
and specifically in this case uh is due
to the uh disadvantage of using uh open
loop policy at open loop Dynamics and
open loop policy planning so what
exactly is the advantage or disadvantage
of being open loop so here we have a
proposition that quantifies that and it
turns out that the advantage of being
close loop is exactly related to um The
Information Gain so how did we get this
um so basically we start with a one-step
decision making and in that setting the
advantage of being a Clos Loop is
basically the expected value of perfect
observation which is the difference
between an expected value given perfect
observation and without and then we can
rewrite this as a linear combination of
the difference between the updated
belief and the prior belief and if we
apply some bounds here then we can uh
rewrite we we can upper bound this as
the expected Information Gain and that's
how we got this and if we ACR this along
the planning Horizon then we basic
basically multiply this by the effective
planning Horizon 1 overs 1 minus gamma
um so that's how this is obtained um so
this is actually very interesting
because it give us a clue that if we
want to improve the open loop policy
while still committing to open loop
Dynamics then one very reasonable thing
we can do is to change its reward and
the Very obvious choice for changing its
reward is to Simply add uh is to Simply
make up for uh The Information Gain that
it loses by using the open loop Dynamics
and add that back to the reward
function um and that and once you do
that then basically you got the efp
objective function in
here um so to be able to formally show
that the efu policy which is simply the
open Lo policy plus an information
reward and show that how how much it
improves on top of the open loop policy
we need to make a few assumptions so the
first assumption we make here is on the
preference specification so basically we
need to what this assumption says is
that uh we need to make sure that uh if
we still want the EF agent to be go
directed then we need to set the
preference in such a way uh so that the
gain in pragmatic value uh after a
belief update is always greater than the
loss and Information Gain after a belief
update so this way we make sure that
agent focus on a task and doesn't get
distracted by collecting information
that's potentially not useful for the
task and then the second set of
assumptions are introduced to make us um
able to compare the open loop policy and
EF policy on more of equal ground so the
first assumption is that the
we're going to assume that the EF policy
commits no more uh or rather it does no
worse in terms of policy Advantage
compared to the open do policy and the
second assumption says that the
Information Gain value along the horizon
is always going to be greater than some
values uh so again these things are
introduced just for us to better compare
the two policies and with all of these
assumptions and the previous insights we
have our main result here which gives
the regret bounce for the open loop and
the EF policies and so we see here that
for both the open loop and EF policies
we have a term that's linear in the
policy era and quadratic in the uh
Information Gain but the difference uh
between EF policy and open loop policy
is that the EFC has an additional term
which is uh a minus L something uh that
that is linear in the information gain
so basically the upper bound is being
reduced by this linear this term that's
linear in the uh Information Gain so
that's how much uh the EF policy
improves upon the open policy uh which
makes it a better approximation to the
base optimal policy than open Lop policy
um yeah so that's that's the main
results and the main idea uh in the
paper so we'll just close up with some
uh discussions that might be interesting
to people from different
communities um so the first interesting
observation is that um this view of EF
as an approximation to the base optimal
policy actually connects back to a lot
of work people have done in pomdp
planning so the thing about PDP planning
that's very tricky is that even though
mdp policies are very easy to compute as
soon as we introduce partial observation
it just becomes extremely difficult to
compute the um optimal optimal policy
that would optimally trade off
exploration exploitation so people have
explored a bunch of humanistics and one
of them is called the Dual mode
controller where you would design an ad
hoc rule to switch between uh
exploration mode and exploitation mode
so for the explor and and uh and and
that switch is being uh determined by
the entropy of your belief with some um
chosen
threshold and for so for the exploration
mode um um
you essentially take arcmax of the
current belief so that's the state that
you believe is most likely to be the
current state and you would simply
choose an action uh from the mdp policy
which we know is easy to compute but if
the belief entropy is higher than your
threshold then you would take an action
to minimize the entropy of the next
belief so you can read this as something
that's very similar to maximizing the
gain of information in the next
period uh another interesting framework
again from the P DP literature is that
um some people have realized that there
just there there's certain types of
behavior that just cannot be modeled as
um obtaining uh as as reward driven um
and and usually what happens here is
that you want these agents to actually
minimize the end U entropy of their
beliefs or maximize the information gain
so this is usually called Ro pump DP or
active sensing so the objective function
in this um in this framework usually is
just to minimize entropy of belief but
not the onestep belief entropy rather
the cumulative belief entropy along the
entire planning Horizon so something
very interesting about this is that um
this term if if we
introduce um a uniform prior belief that
doesn't change over time steps then
minimizing belief entropy is actually
proportional to maximizing the expected
K Divergence between an updated belief
and a uniform prior belief so this looks
really similar to The Information Gain
objective uh in efv and usually what
people do is that um instead of just
minimizing belief entropy depending on
whether we have any requirements for uh
getting rewards we would do a waited sum
of the reward term and the belief
entropy term and that and when you do
that that objective is essentially the
uh belief action reward uh in in the in
the EF
case um so the one final thing is that
actually goes back to active inference
so the formulation of active inference
that I have introduced I I qu the
vanilla active inference and it's also
the active inference uh the the the
version of active inference that's
currently in uh the main branch of
imdp um but um in 2021 um people have
proposed A variation of active inference
called the sophisticated inference and
basically what it does is that uh it
maintains the um reward plus Information
Gain as the uh belief action reward but
he actually uses the Clos Loop belief
Dynamics I think there's a sentence
somewhere in the paper that says that
the difference between sophisticated
inference and the vanilla active
inference is that a
would plan not for future States but for
future beliefs so if that's the case
then
um uh it it's essentially using the same
belief transition Dynamics as the base
optimal U belief mdp um so for
practitioners then um there's a
potential problem with sophisticated
inference which is that um now you're
basically being based optimal with your
belief Dynamics but you're adding an
additional um term in your reward which
means that if the base if the behavior
that's supposed to be produced by the
base optimal policy you're now ruining
it with the additional information gain
term um so basically the concern is that
agent uh sophisticated INF agent would
try to get too much information at the
detriment of uh getting less reward
because you would spend more basically
you would spend more time uh collecting
information than focusing on a task um
but um essentially what comes to the
rescue is our old friend uh the
temperature parameter so depending on
how you set uh the Precision of your uh
preference distribution for example
using a temperature parameter of a
softmax distribution then you
essentially construct a weighted uh
essentially a waiting of um the reward
term versus The Information Gain term so
so if your preference is very precise
with a very low temperature then or in
this case a very high value of lamba
then you're essentially saying that I
only care about the reward I don't care
about the information gain and in this
and and and if you do this then
sophisticated inference just becomes
exactly equivalent to the base optimal
policy um so um so essentially the
Lambda temperature term Lambda
interpolate based optimal policy for uh
reward seeking Behavior versus
information seeking uh Behavior if you
have uh low Lambda and this essentially
makes um sophisticated EF a strict
generalization of the base opal policy
uh so that's everything I wanted to
discuss I think uh so the final slide is
for people who are interested in uh more
uh the basics of active infants and also
the connection between active infants
and RL I have uh two blog posts to offer
that some people perhaps find
helpful yeah thanks
again awesome thank
you all right I'll read a first question
from the live chat and then I'll read
some questions I wrote and some other
questions from the live chat
so Andrew wrote you mentioned that we
should set preferences such that the
pragmatic value outweighs the
information value lost after the agent
has already achieved that information
value so that the agent does not become
too focused on seeking information
rather than achieving a goal can this
strategy risk the agent getting stuck in
a local Optimum by setting preferences
which mitigate information seeking
okay I I think something slipped her
mind because because it appears to me
that the question is somewhat reversed
so if I'm getting the idea right so
you're saying that if the agent somehow
gets stuck in a local Minima along a
trajectory to get reward then one thing
you can do is to change for example The
Waiting be between the reward term and
the um the Information Gain term so that
it um essentially switches the mode to
focus on getting information and
hopefully bounces itself out of the uh
the local Optima is that
right it could
be um and then is the question whether
that's a reasonable thing to do whether
there's a way to automatically do it um
or or is is that what what you're
looking for I I don't know yeah where
where and how does preference learning
and scaling come into play so to to keep
these kinds of epistemic and pragmatic
dualities if there is going to be a
unified imperative for policy selection
that's projecting onto a a set of EF
values then how do you wait the
epistemic and pragmatic value like in
training and in in
deployment yeah I think this is an open
question I don't think anyone has done
very convincing work on this topic
specifically so I know about One thread
of work from uh Carl's people uh
essentially they have a way to uh
Define uh an update rule for the the
temperature parameter or the Precision
parameter so basically what happens
there is that if um you end up in a
situation
where um your variational free energy
which quantifies the accuracy and
essentially the accuracy of your
predictive model if variation of the
energy
decreases uh which means that your um
starting to observe signals that uh
constantly violates your model of the
environment then you would choose
actions in a way that's more stochastic
so there are ways to derive such rules
um from uh the view where uh of um this
notion of free energy unifies perception
action so people from Carl's lab has
derived rules like this um and then uh
there's also a work from nor and um uh I
think it's called um uh I can't remember
what it's called but basically what that
work does is uh it's trying to use Basi
and updating to learn uh the preference
as the agent interacts interacts with
the environment so basically the agent
would start by having some preferences
about it about what states or
observations to achieve in the
environment uh and as the agent
interacts with the environment it would
actually refine its own model its own
preference model rather than its model
of the Dynamics of the environment um
but something very tricky that happens
there is that um so she did the
experiment in this environment called
frozen lake uh so basically you're
walking on a frozen lake and there are
holes on a lake and if you somehow step
into that hole you would fall or die and
then um an agent that learns the
preference in that environment basically
learns that it prefers to fall into
holes um so so that doesn't really make
a lot of sense um if your goal is to
maximize reward for staying alive but it
makes sense in a sense that agent just
builds
uh a preference model that uh is
essentially in compliance with uh with
what actually happens in the environment
so it's kind of Self evidencing in the
wrong way um so do either of these two
approaches um provide a practical way to
automatically tune a temperature
parameter uh to balance yourself out of
a local Optima like you said I I don't
think either of them do that
um so so I don't I don't think I have a
comment that like firmly addresses this
at the moment I do know that um people
who actually more work more on the Basin
arel side they have um done some work uh
to derive approximations to exact um
basing RL and in doing so they were able
to derive some automatic temperature
tuning rules um to achieve that so if
you're interested I believe the persons
is Ian
alband um but I can I can be wrong but
just look for Bas in R literature um
it's it's a paper
that um essentially derives um U A Basin
RL version of soft acor
critic awesome thank you and another way
to address that is to avert slash a void
structurally so that like a blood sugar
distribution could be loaded with high
pragmatic value and is distribution
could be driven by high epistemic value
in hierarchical models so it isn't that
every single model is just Loosely
describing all of this cluster of
undefined processes this is really
getting to the distributional level and
then if a distribution really does have
such a challenging situation that it has
to be
tight and refined and then make a large
jump to an area it's never been I mean
those are the challenging situations and
that's where these other techniques and
methods can be brought into play however
those are the challenging ones and and
that is not even necessarily needed for
simpler settings um well thanks again
for the really instructive and
informative presentation to kind of just
restate I saw the big move
as grounding in the full
observability conditions and the
analytic situation for the Markov
decision process for the mdp so certain
kinds of guarantees exist that
are um as as they should be slightly
weakened with the partial observability
introduction of observables and latent
States so how is it possible to use some
of the techniques patterns guarantees
etc for full observability on a
partially observable situation and the
move is kind of to consider the
parameterization of the generative model
as a fully observable setting which is
what it is in like the programming
environment whereas if if even part of
it were obscured then even that would be
a partially observable setting so by
treating like the
ABCDE partially observable mdp that we
see in the textbook and and all this
work by treating that as fully
observable essentially to the proof
finder exactly Thank You by by treating
the full State updating of the PDP now
that bottomup semantics of those
variables might be the probability that
this happens or the prob ility that this
maps to that so still it is about
partial observability but then
considering that object in its fully
observable condition to
itself then you can see that no regret
situation where there's no policy
advantage and one's own sense
making didn't have a disadvantage and an
expert evaluating one sense making
didn't have a disadvantage so in those
situations the
learner characteristic is zero regret on
the policy and on the sensemaking side
and then there's a kind of imperative
which is the distance from the expert
sense making and policy
selection because it's basically like
what would have been the expert policy
and sense
making if it would have been fully
observable and then the pmdp P PDP
reduces to an
mdp yeah that's precisely the um the the
strategy
so um planning in uh pum
DPS um can be turned into planning in
mdp is just a much more difficult mdp
you don't get it away with any of the
difficulty of planning in belief
mdp um because uh now the state space is
uh essentially H essentially has um
countably infinite uh cardinality uh
which means that there's no way for you
to uh compactly represent your uh
beliefs over multiple steps or your
value functions so it doesn't make any
of that or any practical applications
simp
but it does offer a very nice theoretic
technique to to better understand uh the
different kinds of tweaks you can you
can do to the theoretically optimal uh
base optimal
policy cool and and then another
connection is with the Dual mode
switching so in like chapter five of the
textbook in their
neuroanatomy they show one schema of how
dopamine level regulates sort of a
system one system two Thinking Fast
thinking slow shift in the thinking fast
mode
observations expected or otherwise don't
even need to be considered you can just
sample directly from the policy prior
from habit and then even to engage
expected free energy use G to update
policy prior into a policy posterior so
even in even to consider possible future
actions and observations that's a
deliberative mode it's dealing with
intangibles and doing computations that
where habit will suffice can just be
done so then by by proxy you can use the
observation entropy and just say if the
observations are within this acceptable
threshold there's no reason to step
outside of habit and then where
observations start to become surprising
in this way then a
deliberative execution per policy can
happen yeah so
um I I think this is very interesting
like um so mode switching or like um
self um essentially self
selection of how much compute resources
you put into at at test time or at
runtime um is a very interesting topic I
know Alec has done some work on um like
once you amortize a policy you can still
choose to refine your policies on on
online uh and so on and so forth and and
it also makes a nice connection between
what's happening with like large
language models now day you have like
so-called like post training you can do
a lot of stuff so for example in what's
called best of end sampling where you
sample a ton of uh outputs from the
policy and then you use that reward
function of score which one um is better
and then choose the output that instead
of all the other um completions that you
have sampled and then basically the more
completions you sample the more likely
um you'll get a completion that's um
going to be scored Higher by the test
time reward function and then you can
basically decide okay what what's the
trade-off I'm going to make between my
test time compute that's been used to do
a ton of sampling which is very
expensive versus um um versus the the
potential improve Improvement in reward
that I'm going to get um so this this is
very interesting um but I I don't think
um like
in in the active frence Community people
have done enough uh principled work uh
to overcome with the principal framework
to uh allow an agent to dynamically
adjust their uh computational resource
and time uh on the flight so I would
actually encourage and also I don't
really understand it myself so I would
encourage people to do more work uh
along this along this direction uh to
figure out what is the generative model
uh that allow people to do test time
adaptation of Computer Resources and so
on cool yeah that's very interesting and
gets into like system design like is it
the agent that's estimating how much
resources would be useful for it or is
there an estimator that's making a
secondary judgment um I'll read a
question from the chat Shri Hara wrote
thanks for the talk rant in your
expertise from an engineering
perspective what are your comments on
building a deep active inference agent
versus a deep RL agent like
dreamer um yeah so I I think the the
word deep sometimes mean different
things um in different communities so in
uh so so early in the day deep active
inference um used to mean using like
deep networks to approximate certain uh
distributions or amortize certain
distributions um in active inference
agents
um uh I I think over and then over the
years the meaning of deep uh has shifted
so now I think within active inference
Community deep means having multiple
levels of hierarchy uh sometimes it also
means planning
along uh a longer uh temporal depth um
yeah so um so I think I think um being
hierarchical is actually pretty
difficult I I again I I don't know of a
very um nicely principled and still
um working way to um make agents um
hierarchically deep uh and and also its
first principle in a sense that it can
be automatically discovered uh from data
I have tried to do some work um but I
haven't uh found a way in which the
hierarchy doesn't uh collapse uh usually
what I found is hierarchies tend to
collapse and things actually like
anything that you can portray as
hierarchical can also be represented in
a flat way so I would again encourage
people to do more work in that direction
but in terms of just comparing um the
VAR ious tools and also way to hybrid
active inference with uh with neuronet u
that people have done versus agents so I
think
um basically a lot of people's view of
dreamer versus you know deep active
inference uh that many people have
implemented is that dreamer is so
similar to active inference especially I
I can't remember if which version of
Dreamer
uh and if it does um use an Information
Gain termin a planning objective and if
it does then uh you basically cannot
tell whether there's any difference
between dreamer and deep active
inference um so so in a sense even Carl
has mentioned it sometimes that dreamer
is basically like um some variations of
um an active inference agent I would I
would point but I would point out that
there's one aspect of dreamer which uh
makes it a little bit um um
theoretically suboptimal but it might
works well in practice because because
of that suboptimality is that um dreamer
doesn't perform belief stat planning as
as most uh deepl systems don't perform
belief space planning uh they perform
State space planning because if you look
at the the policy architecture of
dreamer the policy is not conditioned on
a representation of belief it's
conditioned on a single or multiple
particles sample from the posterior um
so that um in theory would lead to a
slightly different exploration Behavior
but I'm not sure uh how that actually
behaves and the different difference it
makes in practice so if you're
interested in that and if you want to
make deep Ro agents actually do belief
space planning which I personally have
some interested in uh I would encourage
you to look at some of the work from
Shimon whitson's lab uh from Oxford uh
they have done a lot of um belief space
planning of De agents so for people who
I I think PE some people in The
Institute might noce there's an
algorithm called very bad uh that uh the
active influence folk has uh cited most
multiple times so that essentially cames
out of Shimon wion's lab um and and in
that architecture the agents policies
condition on a belief representation as
opposed Asos to to state
representation awesome thank you yeah um
a kind of short comment and thought on
this theory and practice like you
mentioned multiple name spaces that
collide with deep active inference
sometimes people are using neural
network approximators sometimes that's
called amortized inference and then
there's sort of in terms of model depth
people could be talking about
hierarchical like hierarchical basian
models they could also be talking about
temporal depth so whether it's more
layers of the cake on this time slice or
whether it's however many layers the
cake with more time slices and then you
kind of brought in a twist with like
however hierarchies can be flattened we
see that all the time in Matrix
operations where submatrices are used to
flatten all kinds of things and then
similarly in planning there can be a
thicker presence or habit and heris STS
can be learned such that planning like
Behavior can be emulated with with less
depth so that's just so interesting like
the fact that these formalisms can go
and deep in space and time is really
just like an
initial surveying of spaces and just
saying within the infinite policy
Horizon situation this and this and this
will be the case and then it's a purely
empirical engineering question whether
time Horizon of 1 2 3 4 5 has what
computational trade-offs and needs so
it's just like so amazing how the math
has already
sketched out some of the
dimensions and then within the space of
what is sketched out it's an engineering
question almost
alone and there's still theoretical
differences to clarify this entangle but
even those alone don't map obviously to
Performance adequacy or advantage in the
real world or for any given data set so
it's kind of like fun to research and
discuss this underlying layer
which gives rise to those engineering
results at the same time though
imagining that a certain graph or
equation has a certain output on a
certain data set is is hopeful um and
then also I think it connects to the low
and the high road like with Carl's
mention about different architectures
that recapitulate and get to their own
syntheses and combinations of what we
call pragmatic and epistemic value or
maybe what in the energy based learning
energy based models they they might use
more like you presented with the energy
and entropy decomposition it's like
those are constructions along the low
road they are model architectures that
get to this common Nexus of being able
to have an imperative which unifies both
epistemic and pragmatic
value the free energy principle coming
from the high road on on the other hand
has no architectural suggestion it's a
partition in the mathematical physics
State space and so it's unsurprising
that there are models that
are similar on through further
to simplified low road constructions
like
pdps because we're all talking about the
same setting agent or interface input
and output with pragmatic and epistemic
component and so it's just interesting
how all of those
architectures even though they they
might not be able to like make I API
calls to each other or like hot swap
different components they have
comparability against the high
road understanding of their belief
updating for the
next observation coming in and action
going out in a fitness context
yeah I I don't have much comments on
like High Road stuff I
personally um would label myself as a
low road
person that's that's awesome
but both roads must be built yeah um
I'll ask another question in the live
chat and then we'll see if there's any
final questions upcycle Club wrote
are there any potential benefits of
implementing sparse coding techniques in
this
framework so I'm not super familiar with
that let me let me Google that real
quick because I do want to see if I can
address that question I I know about
sparse coding and I know the connection
um between that and uh uh vae um stuff
uh so let me look that up real
quick okay so I'm I'm looking at a
tutorial on sparse coding it says that
sparse coding is a class of unsupervised
models for learning uh over complete
representation
representations
um yeah so uh I'm not sure if there's a
way to interact with the um uh with the
the viewer but um
um does that mean that um you're trying
to um so basically learn more
representations than what's sufficient
uh in a way that's kind of similar to
how people are training uh spars Auto
encoders for interpreting language
models nowadays I'm not sure that's uh
maybe I should read on a little bit more
to see what benefits it
offer yeah I'll let you know if any
other information comes in it's an
interesting connection between the
Matrix flattening and the sparse coding
because sometimes when the matrices get
flattened and fused together using the
submatrix representations then they have
sparsity and then that actually just
from an engineering perspective enables
sparse Matrix methods and compression to
be
used so again whether the hierarchical
representation and with a lower
density or a sparer flattened
representation for a given like language
Etc has this or that performance that's
just an empirical question but it's
interesting that flattening gives you a
constructed sparsity even for nonsparse
information and then there's the angle
you mentioned about the
um
interpretability
sparsity and methods to pull out fewer
interpretable characteristics like for
example um yeah yeah did the viewer
respond there no but how about just
um upcycle R better handling of missing
data would be one benefit I can think of
so maybe we'll research and learn
14.2 um yeah what what are your current
research or development
directions um so I'm interested in um
pursuing um this uh view of um principal
planning and uh active inflence a little
more um so basically the reason why I
did the study and wrote this is that I
was trying to understand if there's way
to develop um better planning algorithms
for agents and specifically Bel space
planning for agents uh in a more uh
principled way and
uh and and initially I was doing some
experiments um uh and then it occurred
to me that and then doing experiments
for uh beliefs based planning of active
inference agents and I realized that if
I want to design better algorithms for
active influence agents I actually need
to be have a very precise understanding
of what um the active inference agents
is supposed to do um in a way that's um
uh that's uh not susceptible to all the
holes in active Theory currently so this
um paper essentially contributes to
filling up some of the hes in the um uh
in the theory of active information
planning but just more like planning and
approximate U beliefs based planning in
general so what I want to do as the next
step um for for uh the stuff presented
in this paper is to see if there are
better ways to uh improve planning
capabilities of active inflence agents
and just belief space planning for
agents in general uh that might
um depends on um better um you know
leveraging tools from from variational
inference for planning my leverage tools
from temporal abstraction my leverage
tool tools from
um essentially sparity or sparsification
for inducing more structure it's in a
generative model um yeah but what I
really want to do is just uh make better
planning algorithms for uh for agents
any algorithms that actually work um
that doesn't require a lot of tuning
that um you can just grab and and run it
uh for any ideas you have in mind you
don't have to look for very um spe
specific tools on the Internet and try
it and realize it doesn't it doesn't
really work that
well awesome I'll ask one last last uh
question in in theory or in practice how
is planning for
overaction embodied movement similar and
different than planning for covert
mental
action h
yeah I don't quite understand this so I
I know a recent paper um I think nor is
part of the uh is one of the authors um
I think it's in Europe where uh they
proposed the
hierarchical um model based R agent from
um like that someone inspired by active
inference and then basically what they
do there is to cast um action selection
at the higher level of the hierarchy or
rather well so basically casting that as
covert action
selection um so this doesn't
really um at least if you approach it
from the view of action as an interface
between agent and the environment then
in that sense action always have to um
exist at the lowest level of the
hierarchy right at interface between
agent and environment so it will never
be uh an uh overt action that exist at
inside of the agent at the higher level
um so so that's that's part of the
reason why I say that people should do
more work on hierarchical um models and
hierarchical planning because uh even
though a lot of the existing techniques
work so for example in hierarchical
planning we have the options framework
from uh hierarchical RL uh so what that
does is basically uh decompose planning
uh at the planning of primitive actions
at the lowest level to planning at the
um higher level over more extended
periods of time so basically the higher
level will say execute this task which
then gets translated to a sequence of
lower level actions such as go into the
kitchen grab coffee right that's a
single
movement at the higher level even though
it's a bunch of lower level primitive
movements so I think these um techniques
people have been using in um
hierarchical planning are very appealing
and they actually work pretty well uh
and now with like using language models
to do the option
selection they work very well in
practice but in theory I I I feel like
there's there's still a gap of
how hierarchical
perception model arise automatically
from the environment and how um planning
can just automatically be a part of that
and then how um you know overt mental
actions um you know play a role after
you have obtained uh or learned uh
hierarchical representation of the
environment so all these in my opinion
are open questions I don't think I think
people need to
continue to to address them I don't
think people have addressed them to a
satisfactory extent at the
moment
cool all right thank you this was a
great Stream So till next time yeah
awesome thanks for yeah